International War Crimes Tribunal Records TAM.098
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International War Crimes Tribunal Records
1966-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International War Crimes Tribunal
TAM.098
1.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
In 1967 Bertrand Russell, along with Jean Paul Sartre and Vladimir Dedijer, convened the First International War Crimes Tribunal, held in two public sessions, in Sweden and Denmark. The purpose of the Tribunal, which had no legal standing but which involved the participation of many noted cultural figures and human rights activists, was to expose and publicize war crimes committed during the Vietnam War. After Russell's death in 1970 a second Tribunal, concerned with repression in Latin America, was held in Rome and Brussels in 1974-75. The collection includes records of both tribunals: handouts and reports from various breakout sessions, materials relating to the organization of the tribunals, press releases and clippings.
Arrangement
Series are arranged alphabetically.
The International War Crimes Tribunal Records are organized into 2 series: I, First International War Crimes Tribunal, 1966-1972. II, Second International War Crimes Tribunal, 1973-1975.
Historical/Biographical Note
Two International War Crimes Tribunals were convened by the Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation, the first concerned with the Vietnam War and the second with repression in Latin America.
The first Tribunal was founded in 1966 by Bertrand Russell (1872-1970, an eminent British philosopher whose contributions to the understanding of the foundations of mathematics were crucial for twentith-century philosophy. Russell was awarded the Order of Merit in 1949 and the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1950. He was also well known for his social and political activism, having been imprisoned in 1918 for anti-war activity and in 1961 for his anti-nuclear weapons protests. His appeal in 1966 to convene an International War Crimes Tribunal to expose and condemn American actions in Vietnam was not a surprise, but was widely viewed with skepticism by the public and the press all over the world. Ralph Schoenmann, Russell's secretary, was even accused of manipulating the 94-year-old philosopher.
Russell was not deterred and was able to enlist as members of the Tribunal people from many countries and many backgrounds. Notable are the two presidents, the French philosopher Jean-Paul Sartre and the Yugoslavian jurist Vladimir Dedijer, as well as British historian Isaac Deutscher; Italian Socialist deputy (PSIUP), lawyer and journalist, Lelio Basso; American writer James Baldwin; and Cuban lawyer Melba Hernandez. Around twenty persons were appointed as judges for the Tribunal. Dozens of others took part in the preliminary work, consisting of collecting evidence and testimony on the Vietnam War. Teams were sent to North and South Vietnam, and also to Cambodia, Thailand, Laos, Japan and the United States, from the founding of the Tribunal on November 25, 1966 to the beginning of the second session on November 20, 1967. Two public sessions were held by the first Tribunal – also known as the Bertrand Russell Tribunal on American War Crimes in Vietnam. The first took place in Stockholm, Sweden, from May 2nd to May 10th 1967. The second took place in Roskilde (30 km from Copenhagen), Denmark, from November 20th to December 1st 1967.
Bertrand Russell died in 1970, but Lelio Basso was approached, in October 1971, by Brazilian exiles who were anxious for a new Tribunal to be held on the repression in their country. Basso agreed and some of the members of the first Tribunal enrolled to be part of the second. This time, Lelio Basso served as president, and Vladimir Dedijer, Colombian novelist Gabriel Garcia Marque, Belgian professor of International Law François Rigaux, and French historian Albert Soboul served as vice-presidents. Sartre was made an honorary member. Preparations for the Tribunal lasted two years, 1972-1973. Originally planned to deal only with the repression in Brazil, after the coup d'etat in Chile it was expanded to analyze the situation in all of Latin America.
A constituent meeting took place in Brussels on November 6, 1973. Preliminary reports were given on Brazil and Chile, but also on Uruguay, Bolivia, Panama, Paraguay and Haiti. Two public sessions were held by the second Tribunal. The first took place in Rome, from March 30th to April 6th 1974, and the second in Brussels, from January 11th to January 18th 1975. The official name chosen by the constituents was "Russell Tribunal II on Repression in Brazil, in Chile and in Latin America."
At the end of each of the public sessions, the tribunal reached a "verdict" which addressed the questions stated at the beginning. The first Tribunal concluded not only that United States was committing war crimes in Vietnam, but also that the war was to be considered a genocide against the people of Vietnam. It also judged Australia, New Zealand, South Korea, Japan, the Philippines and Thailand to be accomplices of United States in the war. The second Tribunal stated that the Brazilian, Chilean, Uruguayan and Bolivian authorities were "guilty of serious, repeated and systematic violations of human rights," which violations constituted a crime against humanity.
The Russell Tribunal, severely criticized when it was founded, has, to some extent, become a model, an example for private citizens wanting to make use of evidence, logic and law on an international level, as a means of political protest and publicity. Indeed, the Permanent Peoples' Tribunal was founded in Bologna, on June 24, 1979, as a direct successor of the second Russell Tribunal. In the last decade, a Russell Tribunal on Iraq took place in 2004, and a Russell Tribunal on Palestine was established in 2009.
Sources: International War Crimes Tribunal, against the Crime of Silence: Proceedings of the Russell International War Crimes Tribunal, Stockholm, Copenhagen. New York: Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation, 1968.
Scope and Contents
Series I: First International War Crimes Tribunal, 1966-1972, consists mainly of the minutes of the two public sessions, and of the reports presented as preliminary documents to the Tribunal. It also includes few general files about the Vietnam War. Minutes of the first session are arranged chronologically. Minutes of the second session were published by the Tribunal itself, with reference numbers for each document. Those numbers can be found in the Table of Contents. The documents are arranged by reference numbers. Minutes for both sessions are incomplete.
Series II: Second International War Crimes Tribunal, 1972-1975, consists of various documents on the first public session, including minutes of the opening, the verdict and bulletins, and on the second public session, including a members list, minutes of the opening, and reports on preliminary investigations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1950.217.
Brazil |x Politics and government |y 1964-1985.; Vietnam -- Politics and government -- 1945-1975.; Brazil |x Foreign relations |y 1964-1985.; Chile |x History |y Coup d'etat, 1973.; Latin America |x Relations |z United States.; International War Crimes Tribunal; Latin America |x Politics and government.; Uruguay -- Politics and government -- 1973-1985.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest movements.; International War Crimes Tribunal; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970; Măt trân dân tôc giai phóng miên nam Viêt Nam; Basso, Lelio, 1903-1978; Dedijer, Vladimir, 1914-1990
- Series I: First International War Crimes Tribunal, 1966-1972
  - Bulletin, no. 5-no. 7, Feb 10, 1967-Apr 14, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Canadian Committee: Leaflets, [1966?]-Apr, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Apr 12, 1967-May 5, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Defense Paper: Aziz Kurtha, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - First Public Session: Clippings, Dec 31, 1966-Apr 30, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First Public Session: Investigation Work, Clippings, Dec 30, 1966-[Apr?], 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - First Public Session: Search for a Venue, Apr 14, 1967-May 3, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Final Statement to the Press, May 19, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, May 2, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, May 3, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, May 4, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, May 5, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, May 7, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, May 8, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Minutes, may, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Organization, Apr-May, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Press, Transcripts, May 2-8, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Testimony, May, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - First Public Session, Stockholm: Verdict, May, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Founding: Clippings, Aug 25, 1966-Feb 2, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Founding: Leaflets, [1966?] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fund Raising, [1966?] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Internal Reports, Karen Wald, Jul 2-4, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Leaflets, Nov 25, 1966-Apr 28, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - List of Members, [1967?] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Michigan-Area War Crimes Hearing: Agenda, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Michigan-Area War Crimes Hearing: Clippings, Apr 14, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Preliminary work: Report, Hugh R. Manes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Preliminary work: Report, Leon Matarasso, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Preliminary work: Reports, Gabriel Kolko, Mar, 1967-Apr, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Preliminary work: Report, "Implications [of the Tribunal] for the American Anti-War Movement," Karen Wald, May 11, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: A1B, Opening Message, Bertrand Russell, Nov 20, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: A3B, Inaugural Statement, Nov 20, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: A5B, List of Witnesses, Nov 20, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: B3B, Report, Wilfred Burchett, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: B5B-B10B, Report, M. F. Khan, J.-M. Krivine, R. Pic, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: B13B, Testimony, Marta Rojas, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: B14B, Report on Thailand and the Philippines, Charles Fourniau, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: B19B, Report on Bombardments and Waterworks, Yves Lacoste, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: B21B-B22A, Testimonies, May 29, 1966-Jul, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C1B, Report, "Incendiary Weapons...", Abraham Behar, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C3B-C3aB, Report on Arms Forbidden by International Convention, Yves Jouffa`, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C4A, Report on Crimes towards Civilians, Commission of Inquiry, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C5A-C6B, Report, Gisele Halimi, Nov, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C8B, Report on Warfare Gasses, M. F. Kahn, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C9B, Statutes of the Tribunal, Reformulation, Nov, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C10B, Report on the Trial of Japanese War Crimes, J. Chesneaux, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C11B, Introductory Report to the Second Session, Leon Matarasso, Nov, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C12B-c13B, Reports on Genocide, L. Matarasso, M. A. Aybar, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C14B, Report, "On Vietnam", Guillermo Franck, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: C15B, Report, "Chemical Warfare", Edgard Lederer (dir.), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: D4B-D7B, Testimonies, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: E2B, Report on Japan, Japan Committee, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: E3B, Report on Genocide Crimes in Vietnam, Shingo Shibata, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: E4B, Report about the Tokyo Tribunal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: E5B, Report on Okinawa, Hiroaki Yoshizawa, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: F1A-F3B, On Cambodia, Kouroudeth, N. Sihanouk, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: G1B-G4B, Reports and Testimonies on Laos, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: H1B, Report on the Government of Thailand, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: J1B-J2B, Reports on Korea, Paik Ilkon, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K1B, Letter to Jean-Paul Sartre, Pham Van Dong, Oct 17, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K2B-K3B, Reports on South-Vietnam, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K4B, South Vietnam Peoples Committee for Solidarity with American People, Program of Action, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K5B, Report, National Front for Liberation (NFL = Măt trân dân tôc giai phóng miên nam Viêt Nam), Sep, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K6B-K7B, Reports on War Crimes in South Vietnam, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K8B, Report, Pham Ngoc Thach, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K10B, Statement, South Vietnam National Front for Liberation, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K11B, Message, Nguyen Huu Tho, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: K12B, Declaration, President of the Tribunal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: L2B, Message, Mahmud Ali Kasuri, dec 1, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: List of Witnesses, Nov 23, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: M1B, Statement, Vladimir Dedijer, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: M2B, Answer on the Yugoslav Press, Vladimir Dedijer, Nov 28, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: M3B, Declaration about Ralph Schoenmann, Jean-Paul Sartre, Nov 20, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde, M4B, Declaration about Stokely Carmichael, Jean-Paul Sartre, Nov 27, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: Organization, [Oct?], 1967-[Nov?], 1967 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Second Public Session, Roskilde: Table of Contents, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Statutes, Nov 15, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Third Public Session: Organization, Jun 9, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Witness Summons: B. Russell to Lyndon B. Johnson, Aug 25, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Witness Summons: Jean-Paul Sartre to Dean Rusk, May 3, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Vietnam War: Article from Dagens Nyheter, Sven Oste, May 9, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Vietnam War: Leaflets, [1966?] (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Vietnam War: Poem, "Fathers...", Christopher Logue, Undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Vietnam War: Review of Bertrand Russell's Book, War Crimes in Vietnam, 1966, Jan 4, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Vietnam War: Speech, Ralph Schoenmann, Feb, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Vietnam War: Vietnam Courier, no. 105, Apr 10, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Series II: Second International War Crimes Tribunal, 1972-1975
  - Bulletin: "Russell Tribunal Brazil", n. 1, 2, 4, Feb 1973-Sep/Oct, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - First Public Session, Rome: Correspondence, Harald Edelstam, Mar 7, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - First Public Session, Rome: Minutes, Mar 30, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - First Public Session, Rome: Reports, [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - First Public Session, Rome: Verdict, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Founding: Report, Nov 6, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Minutes (n. 4-5), Jan 11, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Organization, Jan, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, List of Materials (Typescript), [1975?] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Brazil, Comrad Detrez (n. 13), Oct 25, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Brazil, Fernando Andrade (n. 18), [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels, Preliminary Work, Report on Brazil, Jan Knippers Black (n. 15), [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Brazil, Manoel Mello (n. 16), [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Brazil, Sadayiki Satoh (n. 14), [1974] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Chile and Brazil, Fabio Gencarelli (n. 17), [1974] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Chile, A. van Lancker (n. 26), [1973?] (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Chile, F. Debuyst (n. 25), [1974] (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Chile, G. Speranza (n. 22), [1974] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Chile, Van Solinge and Chkounda (n. 28), [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Guatemala (n. 32), [1974] (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Haiti, Ulrick Joly (n.35), Jan, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Legal Aspects, J. P. Dubois (n. 31), Nov 23, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Panama, Xabier Gorostiaga (n. 34), Sep 9-14, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Report on Paraguay (n. 33), Jan 11-18, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Reports on Bolivia (n.10, 11, 20), [1974]-Jan, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Reports on Brazil (n. 9, 12, 19), [1973?]-[1974?] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Reports on Chile (n. 8, 21, 23, 24, 27), [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Reports on Multinational Companies, J.-P. Dubois and P. Ramadier, Buffolo (n. 29-30), [1974?] (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Second Public Session, Brussels: Preliminary Work, Reports on Uruguay (n. 6-7, 37), [1974] (Box 2, Folder 29)